Morris C. McEldowney Military Service in East Asia Photograph Album, 1954-1955 RL.10981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Morris C. McEldowney Military Service in Korea and Japan photograph album
1954-1955
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McEldowney, Morris C., 1905-1986
RL.10981
0.4 Linear Feet
A hand-made photograph album by US Army Chaplain Morris C. McEldowney, dated 1954-1955. The album contains 190 photographs laid down on 172 stiff cardboard sheets, 7.5 x 4 inches, plus 6 small Japanese color woodblock views laid down on three more pages. The candid snapshots, with handwritten captions, are primarily of Seoul, Korea, the 8th Army military base, and the surrounding area. It also contains photograhs of Pusa, Korea, Tokyo, and Sendai, Japan.
Provenance
The Morris C. McEldowney Military Service in East Asia Photo Album was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in December, 2014.
Collection Overview
A hand-made album of 190 photographs laid down on 172 stiff cardboard sheets, 7.5 x 4 inches, plus 6 small Japanese color woodblock views laid down on three more pages. Most of the black-and-white gelatin silver photographs measure 4.5 x 3.5 inches and are candid snapshots of the local people, shrines, public buildings, and marketplaces in and around Seoul. Some of the photographs are non-standard sizes, having been cut and cropped by McEldowney. McEldowney also carefully recorded notes in ink on what he was seeing, providing both historical and personal commentary in the margins of most of the pictures.
Twenty-four photographs are views of sites in Sendai and Tokyo, the rest are of Korea, and the 8th Army compound (Yongsan Garrison) in Seoul. He documented the refugee housing in Seoul, a barber shop set up inside a cave near the Thousand Steps, the Capitol Building constructed by the Japanese, the Korean royal palace (Gyeongbokgung), a white buddha statue located in a rock quarry, the Tomb of the Kings, women doing laundry in the river, and many street scenes.
The photographer captured pictures of U.S. Ambassador to Korea Ellis O. Briggs and his daughter Lucy, and his successor, William S. B. Lacy.Several of the chaplains stationed in Korea at this time also appear in the photographs, including Lewis Durden, Bernie Fenton, and John Woods. There are photographs of the opening ceremonies for the 8th Army Chaplain's Leadership School and Retreat, the DMZ, two Korean sisters who worked as secretaries and interpreters for the army, a YMCA school, and a local Boy Scout troop.
Titles of pages are provided by creator. Notes provided are verbatim transcripts of handwritten captions provided by creator.
Historical note
Morris C. McEldowney (1905-1986) served 17 years as a Chaplain in the US Army, and retired from regular service in 1959. He saw three tours of duty in Europe and one in the Far East.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Korea (South) -- History; Gelatin silver prints; Seoul (Korea) -- Social life and customs; Tokyo (Japan) -- Description and travel; Seoul (Korea) -- History -- Pictoral works; Seoul (Korea) -- History, Military; Sendai-shi (Miyagi-ken, Japan); Seoul (Korea) -- Description and travel; Photograph albums; Pusan (Korea); Korea (South) -- Social life and customs; Military chaplains -- Korea; McEldowney, Morris C., 1905-1986; United States. Army -- Military life; United States. Army. Army, 8th.
- Photograph Album
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains 190 photographs on 172 sheets.
  - 1: Panorama of Seoul Korea from the Namsan 1000 steps (Box 1)
  - 2: Overlooking Seoul shown in Panorama (Box 1)
    In contrast to all the natural beauty, see what man has done to nature. Louie and I stop for a photo overlooking the city shown in panorama.
  - 3: South Gate Seoul (Box 1)
    Part of the wall surrounding the old city. Note: Lady at left in long waisted velvet traditional skirt.
  - 4: RTO Seoul: Main railroad station. (Box 1)
    Showing mountains in background
  - 5: Foot Bridge, Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    Located in the national forest near ancient city wall built in 1398.
  - 6: Barber shop in a cave (Box 1)
    Near the Thousand Steps. The barber probably lives in the cave.
  - 7: City Wall: Seoul, Korea (Box 1)
    Note John Good on wall - center of picture.
  - 8: City Wall: Seoul, Korea (Box 1)
    Wall was built in 1400s sometime
  - 9: The Thousand Steps, Namsan Mountain, Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    Overlooking city, Picture reverse: taken from the lower square
  - 10: The Thousand Steps (Box 1)
    Looking toward the top of Namsan Mountain. The steep cliffs of the mountain formed part of the ancient city wall--is now a national park.
  - 11: Capitol Building (Box 1)
    Sun through a gate in Kyong Bok palace. Capitol building was built by the Japanese and is unused by the present government out of President Rhee's extreme hatred of Japanese.
  - 12: Dome of New Capitol again, May 1955 (Box 1)
    A closer view from another gate in the palace grounds. Kyong Bok palace was built in 1395 and restored in 1865. It's the home of Korean kings.
  - 13: The White Buddha (Box 1)
    This is an Oriental God--an idol, and the priest and acolyte are conducting ritual. It's located N/W of Seoul in a rock quarry some 15 miles from HQ. Although it was mid-afternoon--
  - 14: The White Buddha (Box 1)
    A cold wind was blowing. The 2 Buddhists finished their liturgy and went to their monastery on the rock ledge to R of picture. Picture was taken on icy surface of a stream. Note: liturgical vessels on altar.
  - 15: Kinyon-Bi Memorial (Box 1)
    Surprising architecture is quite typically Korean but its location and size suggest a gasoline fueling station.
  - 16: Kinyon-Bi (Box 1)
    A memorial built in 1902 in memory of King Kojong's ascension. It's a little gem located in a busy street intersection.
  - 17: Jip Okje (Box 1)
    Royal library at Kyong Bok Palace built in 1867 by the Emperor Kojong.
  - 18: Kong Bok Palace, Seoul, 1955 (Box 1)
    Courtyard in front of the palace buildings-- once a garden but rather unkempt at present.
  - 19: Kozie and Koko, the two Miss Ko sisters, May 15, 1955 (Box 1)
    They have very unpronounceable Korean names so the GIs in the office have called them Kozie (R ) and Koko (L). Kozie is our secretary and interpreter leaving in Aug for Shenandoah College Va.
  - 20: Kozie and Koko at the tombs of the Kings last Sunday (Box 1)
    Can you see any resemblance in features between Koreans of yesterday and today.
  - 21: Pagoda Park - Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    13 story pagoda is the largest in Korea. Site commemorates a temple built in 1466.
  - 22: Pagoda Park - Seoul, May 1955 (Box 1)
    Pavilion with pagoda seen through to the rear.
  - 23: The Kyungnoi Roo (Box 1)
    Royal Banquet Hall built in 1412 by Tai Jong at the Kyong Bok Palace behind the capitol building. Damaged during Communist invasion and restored in 1954.
  - 24: Kun Chun Moon palace gate at Kyong Bok., May 1955 (Box 1)
    Built in 1395 and restored in 1865. Stairs lead from either side to the guard tower which commands a view of surrounding terrain as well as palace grounds.
  - 25: Curfew Bell (Box 1)
    dates from 15th century. Located at one of Seoul's busy downtown traffic circles.
  - 26: Pavilion called Hyang Won Jung (Box 1)
    located on an island in a lagoon at Kyung Bok palace. Built in 1867. Bridge restored in 1953.
  - 27: Han River Bridge, Seoul Korea, Mar 1955, March 1955 (Box 1)
    Ann - It was at this point that thousands of Koreans died during the recent war. The Han river lies between Seoul and North K. and safety in the South. Some idiot blew the center span of this bridge 24 hours early and people drowned like rats.
  - 28: Korean Memorial of Han River near Seoul, March 1955 (Box 1)
    River and mountains in the background looking toward Seoul bay and the river. I really do not know what the monument commemorates but one suggestion appears obverse.
  - 29: Tombs of Kings near Seoul - Kozie and Koko (Box 1)
    Monument is to represent the king and the second figure is his chief steward or something. Animals are horses.
  - 30: Tombs (Box 1)
    The flat rock is a table where the family came for ceremonial meal with the departed spirit of dead king. The pagoda type object to L of table is where a light is kept burning.
  - 31: Banquet Hall of the Korean Kings in Seoul (Box 1)
    Located in Kyung Bok Palace. Architecture is classical period built in 1412.
  - 32: Royal Banquet Hall (Box 1)
    in a lily-flecked lagoon in the palace grounds. Kyong Bok Seoul.
  - 33: Stone Lions - Kyung Bok Palace, Seoul (Box 1)
    2 of 16 original lions flanking the Forbidden bridge, guarding the palace.
  - 34: Tomb of the Kings (Box 1)
    In ancient days an overnight journey from Seoul to the East. Located on hills in a quiet valley, nine tombs are preserved marking the burial palace of Korea's rulers. Now preserved as national park.
  - 35: From Guard Tower overlooking Kyung Bok Palace (Box 1)
    L: Forbidden Bridge, R: Audience Hall with stone lions adorning entrance, built 1394.
  - 36: Seoul Zoo (Box 1)
    Located adjacent to Chang Duck palace grounds - favorite picnic area.
  - 37: Street Scene Seoul, Note South Gate in background (Box 1)
  - 38: Street Scene Seoul, December 1954 (Box 1)
    Taken Sunday afternoon in Dec 54.
  - 39: Street Scene Seoul (Box 1)
  - 40: Street Scene Seoul (Box 1)
  - 41: Street Scene Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    Note: East meets West in men's garb. Note: Sign in English reading "Paint Shop" and below same legend in Korean or Chinese.
  - 42: Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    Laborer wearing loaded "A" Frame. All students in Korea wear the student uniform -- lad behind the laborer. Left- Completely Western garb of hatless youth.
  - 43: Homes in Seoul, November 1954 (Box 1)
    Several families share a common inner court surrounded by stone wall and single entrance.
  - 44: Capitol Building Seoul, and the Gate to the Capitol Grounds, November 1954 (Box 1)
    Building is unused today because built by Japanese and a bitter reminder.
  - 45: Laborer with "A" Frame (Box 1)
    Open stall market
  - 46: Street Young Dong Do (Box 1)
    Street vendors, open stall market costume. Chaplain Durden
  - 47: Open Market: Yong Dong Do (Box 1)
    This market extends for 2 city blocks and is jammed with miscellaneous items as you see here and crowds of people.
  - 48: Rice Market: Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    Containers are made of rice straw. The tent is US Army surplus.
  - 49: Refugee Housing Seoul (Box 1)
    Many of the refugees from beyond the DMZ live in cramped temporary shelters in Seoul. City population is swollen beyond capacity. Some live even in caves.
  - 50: Refugees (Box 1)
    Sanitation under normal conditions just doesn't exist and during the rainy season becomes a swampy matrix of germs and infection.
  - 51: Street Scene: Seoul (Box 1)
    Note: 1) No hands - woman in foreground. 2) Student uniform - All children in school are required to wear this uniform - the little girl left of center. 3) Slacks 4)Hair styling 5) Open shop.
  - 52: Street Scene - Seoul (Box 1)
    This picture is almost American or European. It might be almost any American city. Only one thing in picture marking the scene as oriental and that is the hand cart in the center of the picture.
  - 53: Kemchee Market, Yong Dong Do, Korea, November 14, 1954 (Box 1)
  - 54: Kemchee Market, Yong Dong Do, November 14, 1954 (Box 1)
    Bales of Chinese cabbage in background. Other items = red pepper, garlic.
  - 55: Market Scene (Box 1)
  - 56: Street Scene Seoul (Box 1)
  - 57: Street Scene Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    Yes, the man in white is doing exactly what he appears to be doing. And Korea turns its head in unconcern.
  - 58: Korean Character (Box 1)
    An especially good study of Korean types. Papa San with his placid gestures. Young matron - sweet faced. A student in uniform. And the child at the bottom of the picture.
  - 59: Bus stop at Eighth Army (Box 1)
    I tried to catch John beside Miss Korea at the bus stop by my shutter jammed and a second later, he had a telephone pole between them.
  - 60: Rice mat shop, March 1955 (Box 1)
    These rice straw mats serve as floor coverings and mattresses. Rather a typical item of oriental home economy-- not strictly Korean since use and manufacture were introduced by the Japanese.
  - 61: Street Scene Seoul, March 1955 (Box 1)
    Looking toward Nam San Mountain. Ch. W with camera in center of street.
  - 62: Revival Tent, Nam San Mt., March 1955 (Box 1)
    Located just at the top of the thousand steps, this Pentecostal group has indulged the customary emotional excesses even to an attempt to convert Chaplain Durden.
  - 63: Korean "Papa San" Seoul, March 26, 1955 (Box 1)
    Note the EDE-WA shoes, bloused trousers, the white, white robe, hat, beard, and cane. Taken on road to the 1000 steps. Nam Sam or South Mountain.
  - 64: Seoul City Mailman, March 26, 1955 (Box 1)
    As we came along he had just taken mail from the street pillar mail box. J.W. has his attention as I snapped any picture.
  - 65: Young Korea (Box 1)
    He speaks a little English. He wears a wrist watch. He sees much and knows much as is much interested in the world. He loves his barren hills and scrub pines and is willing and capable of fighting.
  - 66: Ancient Korea (Box 1)
    Wears glasses and a "Papa San" hat @ 4000 Hwan. His smile hides a shyness and suspicion of cameras and everything western. He is conservative, suspicious, resists change. He loves the old order, the ancient ways and nurses ancient hatreds including Japan.
  - 67: Draft Oxen, Kemchee Market, Yong dong Do Korea, November 14, 1954 (Box 1)
  - 68: Mongolian Horse, Kemchee Market, Yong Dong Do, Korea, November 14, 1954 (Box 1)
  - 69: Rice Paddie with Oxen Ploughing (Box 1)
    Preparation of the soil for planting rice.
  - 70: Tombs of the Kings, May 30, 1955 (Box 1)
    Two aces visit the Kings. If your wish is a clever title. Taken Memorial Da afternoon 1955.
  - 71: Laundry in River, November 14, 1954 (Box 1)
    Sun 14 Nov 54
  - 72: Laundry near Han River Seoul (Box 1)
    View toward K-16 Seoul City Airport
  - 73: Korea - Youth (Box 1)
    Two little girls too busy to watch the camera. The game is marbles. Place - the busy MSR* playground sidewalk or what passes as a walk -- packed clay. Seoul *Main Supply Route
  - 74: Korea - Age (Box 1)
    Faces of the elderly are very impressive. A mood of serenity and mental alertness is characteristic. There is a certainty and a mark of quality about this old gentleman in spite of clothing. Note padded - or quilted pants.
  - 75: Korean with "A" frame loaded with dustless mops (Box 1)
    Taken on MSR. Note curbing and temporary fence - evidence of war damage. MSR - Main Supply Route
  - 76: Kimchee Pots (Box 1)
    In USA they would be on Grayce's front lawn with petunias. In Korea kimchee is anything but a petunia. Note dress = 1) Korean low, pointed shoes 2) GI jacket, hat 3) Also, beard.
  - 77: Laundry in Han River near K-16 Airstrip, November 7, 1954 (Box 1)
  - 78: Korean laborer with "A" frame Yong Dong Do, November 7, 1954 (Box 1)
  - 79: Laundry, November 1954 (Box 1)
    Little girl was camera shy -- refused to pose and ducked her head as I snapped. K-16 and mountains in background. Nov 54
  - 80: Sunday afternoon on Han River near Seoul, November 1954 (Box 1)
    Picture shows Korean baby sling. Men never carry babies. Women never wear "A" frame.
  - 81: US Army Airforce Postal Service (Box 1)
    This might serve as a front piece to your collection of snaps. Goodness knows you have seen this number often. Through this building -- it's really quite large, goes all the thousands of letters and packages. It's the gateway to my daily visit home.
  - 82: Entrance to Eighth Army Chaplain's Office. Big Durden Little Tree: Chaplain Lewis Durden, roommate at A-37 (Box 1)
  - 83: Eighth Army Compound from chopper pad (Box 1)
    Corner of my house shows at lower left. Quonset below house is mess hall. Office is bldg. in center and to right of cen. racing field.
  - 84: Christmas 1954 Eighth Army Chapel, December 26, 1954 (Box 1)
    Life-size manger scene
  - 85: Taken in front of Army Chaplain office (Box 1)
    Papa San - Jeep driver of No. 35. Mamma San, our housekeeper. Our Mamma San is one to right
  - 86: Yong Dong Do street scene (Box 1)
    Mother and baby - showing baby sling and method of carrying cargo on head. Note bandage on baby's ear. Korean dirt farmer in traditional whites. Note open sewer on left.
  - 87: House Yongsan Seoul (Box 1)
    Street up to latrine down to office. My room and entrance
  - 88: Quarters North Post, Yongsan Seoul, Eighth Army HQ, November 1954 (Box 1)
  - 89: Looking toward North Post from 8th Army Chaplain's office, November 1954 (Box 1)
  - 90: View from office, Eighth Army Chaplain (Box 1)
    Chapel, parade ground, athletic field. Chaplain Bernie Fenton.
  - 91: Headquarters Chapel 8 Army Forward, Seoul Korea, 1955 (Box 1)
  - 92: After Chapel, John Woods (Box 1)
    Headquarters Chapel Eighth Army Forward
  - 93: Headquarters Chapel Eighth Army, Yongsan Seoul Korea, November 1954 (Box 1)
  - 94: Eighth Army HQ Chapel, Yongsan, Seoul Korea, November 1954 (Box 1)
  - 95: Faith Hall: Main entrance (Box 1)
    Note: size of windows. My room is rear corner of left wing, 2nd floor.
  - 96: Retreat center (Box 1)
    Picture taken from mountainside. From left- right Quonset - billets, Chapel - adjoining kitchen and dining room. Right - office and billets for HQ det.
  - 97: Louis Durden, January 1955 (Box 1)
    View from the old city wall overlooking the Han River and K-16.
  - 98: Memorial Gate, Seoul Korea, Feb 55, February 1955 (Box 1)
    Replica of gate appears on 100 hwan notes. Located on road to Musan-ni.
  - 99: "Rocky" (Box 1)
  - 100: Everybody takes pictures of everybody in Korea (Box 1)
    Lt Brennan at right, escort for Dr. Poling.
  - 101: Flight sequence (Box 1)
    Pictures snapped at Eighth Army heliport Fri 24 Dec. Showing John Woods arriving from the 1st marine division.
  - 102: John Woods (Box 1)
    Pictures taken Thanksgiving afternoon on a walk along the MSR. Women working with the paving gang refused to pose so John grabbed one of the shovels.
  - 103: Arrival, April 30, 1955 (Box 1)
    Mary Gryader, administrative assistant (center) with Chaplain Woods and Fay Persons, a friend. The day she arrived at K-14.
  - 104: Home (Box 1)
    Our cottage in the woods. My room is facing road on the rear. Concrete porch faces the Han river and a chain of mountains, now has white lawn chairs and table.
  - 105: Opening Ceremonies Eighth Army Chaplain Leadership School, February 1, 1955 (Box 1)
    Gen Beach giving address, Chaplain Woods invocation
  - 106: Opening Ceremonies Chaplain Leadership School and Retreat Center, February 1, 1955 (Box 1)
    Taken during the singing of "America."
  - 107: Retreat Center view from hills. Opening Ceremony (Box 1)
  - 108: Retreat Center: taken from the hills above the compound, January 26, 1955 (Box 1)
    EV Robie was with me.
  - 109: Ambassador Briggs, his daughter Lucy, and the mayor of Seoul in hospital ward at the time of dedication, February 22, 1955 (Box 1)
  - 110: Lucy with one of the orphan babies in the hospital (Box 1)
    This hospital really is Lucy Briggs' project. Guess she has turned everybody upside down to get the building and the equipment. Baby really looks sick.
  - 111: American Embassy, Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    This is the residence of Ambassador Briggs in American Embassy Compound. Picture was taken on 22 Feb. at time of my visit in connection with the dedication of the Children's Hospital.
  - 112: "Old Glory," Seoul Korea, February 1955 (Box 1)
    American flag on foreign soil -- flying above the snow-covered parade ground in the Eighth Army (forward) Headquarters. Picture was taken from the Eighth Army HQ Chapel, looking toward HQ building.
  - 113: Parade Grounds NQ 8th Army (FWD), 1955 (Box 1)
    Review in honor of Ambassador Lacey, recently appointed American Ambassador to Korea. Honor guard and color guard. Han San mountain in background.
  - 114: Same (Box 1)
    Guard reviewed by Lt. Gen Ferrenbaugh, General Disney, Ambassador Lacey, Second row 8 A G staff. In background - 8 Army Chapel, theatre, library.
  - 115: Dr. Daniel Poling with Mrs. Lutz, missionary, January 23, 1955 (Box 1)
    Photo = at the Presbyterian mission in Seoul. Dr. Ed Adams, Mr. Lutz, Mrs. Lutz, Dr. Poling. Entrance to Adams residence.
  - 116: Chapel dedication, December 26, 1954 (Box 1)
  - 117: Dr. Poling leaves Korea, January 24, 1955 (Box 1)
    Plane is the Batan and field is K-16. Miss Sitler and Chaplain Woods join the group.
  - 118: Dr. Poling precedes the General into the plane (Box 1)
    Note: 4 stars on star. Army commanders plane. Ready to leave -- some officer changed his mind at the last minute.
  - 119: John Woods clowning with an "A" frame (Box 1)
    Note: Expressions on faces of Koreans. Orientals have a sense of humor and know a good joke when they see it.
  - 120: Severance Hospital Reception (Box 1)
    Ambassador and Mrs. Briggs are the two on the inside of foursome. Sue Adams at the L of picture and Ned Adams R. Adams I have mentioned frequently as Deans of Presbyterians here.
  - 121: YMCA School, Seoul Korea, February 1955 (Box 1)
    "Y" runs school for some 1200 children in these squad tent classrooms. Children here are waifs picked up from the streets by Boy Scouts.
  - 122: Children's Hospital Dedication, Seoul Korea, February 22, 1955 (Box 1)
    Youngster in the baby ward, an orphan. This is the hospital that Lucy Briggs was interested in.
  - 123: Scouts with Lanterns, Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    Lanterns have the "Y" triangle symbol and burn candles. Two of the street waifs rescued by the Scouts.
  - 124: Scouts and Waifs, Seoul Korea (Box 1)
    Scout hut in background where the rescued children live until they can be placed in houses.
  - 125: Bride and Groom (Box 1)
    At Retreat Center Chapel. This is the bride who kept the groom waiting 3 hours.
  - 126: Bride in Retreat Center Chapel (Box 1)
  - 127: Thanksgiving Day (Box 1)
    This picture was taken during our walk on Thanksgiving Day. We met the Chaplain (R ) of the G? regiment and stopped for pictures. Background, 8th Army compound.
  - 128: Han River (Box 1)
    Picture taken during one of our Saturday jaunts on the heights overlooking the Chaplain School and the Han River Valley.
  - 129: Christmas Party at the Retreat Center, December 24, 1954. (Box 1)
    Orphans, Miss Ko, Chaplain, Civ. Secretary, and Johnson our clerk as Santa.
  - 130: Orphans, Christmas Party at Retreat House, December 24, 1954. (Box 1)
    Taken shortly after I had retrieved my Samoca from residence of Sigmund Rhee where I had left it inadvertently during my visit with Dr. Blake.
  - 131: Portraits (Box 1)
    At left: Hong Soon Il (Jeep 35), kyung Ae Ko (Secretary), Lee Heung Kuk (House boy), Yang Yong Suk (Jeep 36). Right: Mama san, her son. I don't even know their Korean names.
  - 132: Street scenes, December 1964 (Box 1)
    Left: Yongsan area near 8th Army compound. Right: downtown Seoul. Both pictures show women balancing objects on their heads.
  - 133: Easter Sunrise (Box 1)
    Some of the Easter sunrise service crowd going by the Thousand Steps from the top of Han San.
  - 134: Easter (Box 1)